到了这个六周课程的最后了 在教这门课的过程中我得到了
This brings us to the end of the six weeks
course. I had a lot of fun teaching this
很多乐趣，希望你们也能享受这门课 我十分喜欢这个内容
course and I hope you enjoyed it too. I
really love this material and I always
而且我总是喜欢教授它们 在我们告别之前 让我们快速
enjoy teaching it. Before we say our
farewells, please do a quick review of the
复习一下我们讨论的课题 也研究一下剩下的课题 这里是一个简单的
topics that we discussed and see what's
left to cover. So here's a brief diagram
我们在这门课上所讨论的密码学原件的框图 第一周
of the primitive that we discussed in the
class. If you remember in week one we
我们从伪随机数生成器和流密码谈起 第二周
started off by discussing pseudorandom
generators and stream ciphers. In week two
我们讨论了有关分组密码 我们说到考虑分组密码的
we talked about block ciphers and we said
that the right way to think about block
正确方式是考虑伪随机置换和伪随机函数 我们提到使用
cipher is as pseudorandom permutations and
pseudorandom functions. We said that using
counter mode we can convert a block cipher
into a PRG. And we said that using the GGM
计数器模式可以把一个分组密码编程一个PRG 我们说用GGM
construction. We can construct block
ciphers from pseudorandom generators. Then
构造 我们可以从伪随机数生成器构造分组密码 接着
第三周 我们讨论了有关数据完整性 特别的 我们讨论了
in week three, we talked about data
integrity. In particular, we talked about
MAC 我们研究了利用伪随机函数构造MAC的各种方式
MACs and we looked at various
constructions of MACs from pseudorandom
比如CMAC HMAC 和PMAC等等 我们也讨论了
functions like the CMAC, the HMAC, the
PMAC constructions and so on. We also
防碰撞 我们说到防碰撞性质可以用来获得
discussed collision resistance and we said
that collision resistance can be used for
制度存储中需要的数据完整性 基本上 你可以
data integrity where one has access to
read-only memory. Basically, you would
利用碰撞稳固的杂凑函数对数据进行杂凑 把杂凑值
hash the data using a collision resistance
hash function; write the hash into
写到只读的存储里 接着 当你希望验证数据的认证性是
read-only memory. And then later, when you
want to verify authenticity of your data,
你就把数据的杂凑值与写入只读存储的杂凑值进行比较 接着
you just compare its hash to whatever is
written in read-only memory. Then in week 4
第四周 我们讨论了如何把完整性和保密性结合起来 特别的
we talked about how to combine integrity
and confidentiality, in particular we
我们谈到了把加密和MAC结合起来构造我们所谓的
kinda talk about to combine encryption and
MACs to build what we called Authenticated
认证加密 我告诉你们在实际中 最重要的对称密码
Encryption and I told you that really in
practice, the only foremost Symmetric
你能用的就是认证加密 基本上
Encryption that you're allowed to use is
Authenticated Encryption. Basically,
encryption that's only secure against
eavesdropping attacks is not generally
只能抵抗窃听攻击的加密并不安全
secure, you must always also guard against
tampering and as a result, you should only
你必须能够抵抗篡改 于是 你只能用
be using Authenticated Encryption modes to
do Symmetric Encryption. So that was the
认证加密模式做对称加密 我们后面变换了课题讨论了
end of week four. And then for weeks five
and six, we switched topics and talked
密钥交换和公钥加密 特别的 第五周
about key exchange and public key encryption.
In particular, in week five we talked
我们讨论了陷门函数和Diffie Hellman协议
about Trapdoor Functions and the
Diffie-Hellman Protocol [within??] the
也讨论了有关的数学课题以解释这些是怎么工作的
Mathematics that are necessary to explain
how those things work. And then in week
第六周我们讨论了如何从陷门函数构造公钥加密和
six we talked about how public key encryption
can be built from trapdoor functions and,
Diffie-Hellman协议 我想重点提一下
the Diffie-Hellman Protocol. I wanna
emphasize that the key exchange protocols
第五周我们看到的密钥交换协议只能防止窃听攻击而永远
that we saw in week five are only secure
against eavesdropping and should never be
不应该在现实中使用 实际上 第8周我们会看到认证的密钥交换
used in practice. In fact in week eight
we're gonna see authenticated key exchange
协议 那些协议才能在实际中应用 比如
protocols and those are the ones that are
actually used in the wild for example in
SSL协议和类似的协议 但是第五周我们看到的协议
SSL and other protocols like that. But,
the ones that we saw in week five should
就永远不要在真实应用中用 我们研究这些简单密钥
never actually be deployed in the real
world. The only reason we looked at those
交换体制的原因是作为陷门函数和
simple key exchange mechanisms was as
motivation for trapdoor functions and
Diffie-Hellman群的例子 现在你这道了我们后面还有四周
Diffie-Hellman groups. Now as you know there
are four more weeks to the full crypto
的课以完成整个密码学学习。第七周我们会讨论有关
course which we're gonna do at a later
time. In week seven we're gonna talk about
数字签名和验证数据的方式，这种方式使得任何人都可以
digital signatures and how to authenticate
data in a way that anyone can verify that
验证数据的来源 接着我们会讨论认证的密钥交换
the data is authentic. Then we're gonna
talk about authenticated key exchanges as
如我前面所说我们会讨论用户认证性 如何管理口令
I said then we're gonna talk about user
authentication, how to manage passwords,
一次性口令 挑战相应协议 接着我们会讨论
one time passwords, challenge-response
protocols. Then we'll talk about various
各种各样的隐私机制 如何证实你是你自己但是却不泄露你是谁
privacy mechanisms. How to authenticate
yourself without revealing where you are,
如何在不泄露你自己身份的情况下签名等等 在那个部分
How to sign in a way it doesn't reveal who
you are and so on and so forth. And in this part
为了构造某种功能块 实际上我们会讨论
of the building blocks for some of these
mechanisms, actually, we'll talk about
零知识证明 它是在密码学中广泛使用的达到常用目的一种工具
zero-knowledge protocols which is kind of
a general purpose tool that's used very
但是 我们说 密码学比这些个核心课题要
widely in cryptography. But let's just say
that crypto goes way beyond this core
深远得多 实际上 有很多很多课题我很希望跟大家
topics and in fact, there are many, many
more topics that I would love to tell you
说说 如果时间够的话 所以我这里做了这么一个短短的列表
about if there was enough time. So I made
this kind of a short list here and this isn't
这都不全面 有太多的东西需要讲了
even an exhaustive list. There are many
other things that I would like to tell you
如果有需求 我可能会再做一个进阶的密码学课程
about and so if there's enough demand, I
might even run an advanced crypto class
一般我是给研究生做的，能够覆盖这些
which is usually what I do for graduate
students which would cover these more
进一步的课题 实际上有可能明年什么时候就可以了
advanced topics but that would actually
take place sometime next year so stay
所以，请大家关注 我会在开始的时候发通知 所以 我最后要说的
tuned and I will send announcements on
when that's coming. So my final words of
关于这个课程的是 记住我这门课的主要观点 密码学是强大
course remember my main message from this
class. And that crypto is a tremendous
的工具 但是你用的时候一定要消息 如果你使用
tool but you should always be careful when
you use it. If you implement crypto
不当 系统能好好工作 但是
incorrectly, the system will work
perfectly fine. It would be no way to
除非有攻击者试图攻击你的系统 你是不会知道它是不安全的
tell that anything is wrong except when
attacker is trying to attack the system,
可能很容易就被攻破了 因此密码学是这样一种科学
it might be easily breakable. And so
crypto is one of these things where a
你了解不够就非常危险 确保你正确地使用密码学
little bit of knowledge is quite
dangerous. It's quite important to make
是非常重要的 而这么做的方法就是确保
sure you get the implementation correctly
and one way to do that is to make sure
总有人帮你查看你密码应用的代码和设计 找出所有的bug
that always other people review your code
and your designs to find any bugs in the
甚至系统设计中一般的bug 最后
crypto implementation or even more general
bugs in the system design. And finally
我还有把这句话留给大家 永远不要发明自己的
I'll leave you with these parting words, that you should never ever invent your own
密码或者你自己的模式 你也永远不要应用自己的密码和
ciphers or your own modes and you should
never even implement your own ciphers or
模式 尽可能全部使用标准 尽量
your own modes. Try to stick to the
standards as much as possible. Try to
使用标准算法应用 如果你
stick to standard implementations of those
algorithms as much as possible and if you
不得不脱离标准 那就确保有充足的第三方审核你
have to deviate from that, then just make
sure there's sufficient third party review
的工作 好 在这儿我该说再见了 一般
of what you've done. Okay, so I will
say my farewell here. And let me say that
期末考试会在第七周 就是第六周
the final exam will be made available on
week seven, basically, a week after the
视频公开后的一周 期末考试会覆盖所有六周的内容
week six lectures become public. The final
exam will cover material for all six weeks
基本上和作业的形式一样 我希望每个同学都能
and it'll pretty much be the same format
as the problem sets. I hope everybody will
在期末考试上表现好 我们会在你完成这个课业的第一时间
do well in the exam and we will send
certificates once all those course work is
把证书发给你 希望在下一轮课程中见到大家
complete and I hope to see you in the next
iteration of this course whenever that's
好 再见了 依照惯例 请把评价和
made available. So farewell, and as
always, please submit your comments and
建议发在论坛 你们所有的帖子我都会读，而且对
suggestions on the forum. I read all of
your posts and they're very, very helpful
改进这个课程都很有用 希望秋天再见
in improving the course. Hope to see you
in the fall.